I would like to
congratulate the team from Reddit on
their ability to pack a
hall they're going to have to and
they're going to have to stand in the
back it's an SRO crowd welcome to the
second
talk I already named their company we
have now I've forgotten my names because
I left my phone over there Doug cliff
and
Chris thank you Chris from Reddit you
may take it
away hello oh that works okay hi
everyone I'm Doug and intro slide um
that's me on the left uh you can find my
stuff there uh my Reddit username even
if you want to DM me um but I'm software
dog everywhere uh Chris Chris is a infra
guy on our team and
Cliff Cliff uh works on General backend
development and helps us uh with all
kinds of things and search um so we're
part of roughly the SR search relevance
team in at shop at Reddit and um Chris
confused me it's his fault uh Chris and
I used to work together at Shopify so uh
and uh yeah we're going to talk today
about learning to rank and really what
we're going to talk about is we're going
to be pretty upfront with a lot of our
failures um we're going to talk about
sort of how you do this at scale uh and
how you add it to a system that is
already mostly working at scale um of
course at Reddit we have like thousands
of queres per second we have 19 years of
post we just have tons of data so it's
not trivial anytime we need to add
something it's a bit of steering a giant
Cruise liner away from things um
and you know let's talk a little bit
about what Reddit uh content looks like
so of course you might imagine we have a
lot of text Heavy informational content
um and that's true we do have a lot of
text Heavy informational content uh but
it's a bit different than just like you
know normal question answering um there
we also get a lot of the normal like
social network kind of searches so it's
interesting people come up and they
imagine that what we do is always such
and such Reddit you know when people add
Reddit to their Google search that we're
trying to to necessarily replace that
but people do use Reddit search in a
different way they use it for like what
is the latest on this topic in the same
way you might have you know go to
Twitter or whatever your favorite social
network is to kind of see what people
are talking about um so recency
popularity is very important also really
important is just like in this age of AI
we have uh Reddit is the anti-ai in a
lot of ways it is the subjectivity the
long of Human Experience of like what a
specific human being experienced about
something uh whereas if you go to chat
GPT you're going to get sort of a
generic Wikipedia tone of answer of
something um but you get all the
insanity of human beings a very long
tale of like what headphones I liked or
this person looking for help with their
golden retriever uh you get um queries
like it mental health like why am I so
sad it really ranges from all kinds of
things and uh we're in this system we're
trying to solve these problems and
there's lots of things we can do to
solve these
problems that are a combination these
problems are a combination of normal
text retrieval uh but also social
network and recency all of these signals
are really important to us we're in the
system where this is our sort of like
where we're headed at least the first
version of our machine learning is
search system whatever we want to call
it
and I want to because I know people will
ask about Vector search which is over to
the right but we are on the left we are
talking about LTR with lexical features
the boring old 25 stuff and the
stuff that are is still really important
but not
necessarily uh The Cutting Edge or
bleeding edge of what we're talking
about these days but it's still really
important and it's really important for
us to get like fundamentals down for
ranking and we're going to talk about Mr
ml model um literally this is a bunch of
emojis because I don't believe in clip
art anymore emojis exist um and Mr ml
model is going to say I want to improve
your search relevance so how do we do
that first we need to get training data
right we need a bunch of like results of
like search results what's relevant
what's not for these queries here's uh
keybridge and like some labeled results
are these any
good and uh we need some information to
like generalize so like you've given me
examples of what's good or what's not
why is it good why is it bad cuz uh
we're not just repeating training
examples we're trying to basically teach
this ml model a skill like if you see
stuff that looks like this it is
relevant if you see stuff that doesn't
look like this it is not relevant so
really modeling an ml space is about
generalizing um patterns and looking for
General patterns so we need all these
features what was the bm25 score of the
title did the subreddit match the query
at all uh what is the title match in the
keyword did match one or zero how many
hours ago was the post all of these like
Notions of things that we know go with
relevance and there's all kinds of
things we could theorize about
that um and finally um and the part that
a lot of us in the data in ml World take
for granted is somehow I have to ye it
into production and get it to rerank
results um it turns out that's not as
easy as just ye and we'll talk about
that um and of course of course we can
easily have a garbage in garbage out
where if we don't think much about the
stuff on the left we'll just get garbage
on the right right Mr ml model is not uh
it's it's clippy clippy is not going to
be it's not going to be super smart with
uh with giving it garbage examples and
if we do amazing things we can get you
know you can make amazing search results
right so
um it's also not even just about ml I
want to be really clear that a lot of
times I think people make the mistake
with LTR of like trying to run before
they walk and walk before they crawl but
LTR I always see as a forcing function
for increasing the maturity of a team's
practices around these because we have a
tool like cupid which I have the T-shirt
of uh and Cupid's just a manual
relevance tuning tool and a lot of what
we got have we gotten over the this
whole LTR project is not even like that
we a model that ranks results is that we
have really good labeled uh evaluation
data and we have a notion of things that
might improve relevance and we can learn
from our model and just add that to our
core retrieval too and that will also
Drive uh incremental experiments so a
lot of the times it's the experiments
that we found along the way of shipping
an ml model that are some of the most
impactful
things so um going to go through this
talk most first I'm going to talk about
training data feature selection we're
going to talk a lot about getting these
models into production and then I'm
going to talk about like where we are
now and sort of like the painful lessons
we've learned uh and what our next steps
are going to
be so um uh search benches our offline
evaluation tool but like this is the
graphic I share with the team all the
time uh that the reason that we need to
care about offline evaluation or some of
these core practices is because the
teeny tiny tip There's an actual model
that we TR
but there's this whole Foundation of
knowing what relevance even means for
our team or what corresponds to
relevance what features go with
relevance and really that's just classic
relevance work so um what we spent a lot
of time doing was making sure that our
offline evaluation data our judgments as
you may have heard sort of like labeling
what's relevant what's not actually
corresponds to good ab tests and like
points in the right direction because
that's what we're going to train a model
on that's really important so spent a
lot of time just doing manual relevance
work with it um and so one thing we did
was we labeled we have a a a partner
that labeled some search results for us
uh and we got a bunch of to start out
with we got a bunch of these queries
labeled about 20 per query sampled from
the head and tail of our
distribution and that and of itself is
useful just as a test set but more
importantly we sort of learned a formula
that goes with that uh data that we got
so we took that data and we said okay
what does this correlate with in our
analytics and the thing that we most we
found correlated is this uh we what
internally we call good visit but is
really just a click plus dwell that you
may have heard from and we noticed some
other things like there is like a click
is useful but also uh and there's a
little bit of position bias in our
search results so things further down
just generally tend to get clicked less
but mostly it's about the this click
plus 12 and that was a really that made
us feel really good that like hand
labeled results by people outside uh
corresponded with a metric that we use
internally as a success metric so that
became the foundation of our of our
judgments was basically a formula that's
sort of a little bit of this Blended
together you can these are just added
together and
waited um and then we started to use the
judgments we shipped a lot of ab tests
did it go up we tried a lot of like
normal relevance tuning is it seeming to
improve or not and we shipped and
checked to make sure our offline and
online agree and okay this is just
boring it's not really ml but I I don't
care it improves relevance and it's
informed by data and the model for now
is tuned by hand and eventually it will
be tuned by machines but uh this is
important foundational work to do any ml
work in my opinion and finally we would
Yeet that uh finally we could take that
if we felt good about the the uh ndcg
going up in our manual tuning and
actually train a model and ye it to
production and see if that agrees with
online
data um one thing so that's just
generally how we got started on training
data one thing that happened when we
were doing this work is we also had to
do feature extraction and one trick with
feature extraction with LTR is
especially if you're using engagement
data you're always if you have like this
keybridge query every single uh thing
that got engagement probably matches the
text keybridge because that's just what
your current search result shows you so
you do have this like tendency to have a
lot of bias in your search results
towards the the the these features so
every single feature here may be one and
think about what that means if every
keybridge feature is one uh I as a human
like person doing manual relevance
tuning can easily use my brain and say
oh yeah well obviously I want these
these matches are better but a model is
just going to say this feature is
meaningless everything is always one and
I don't have any negative
examples so a really good LTR trick that
a lot of people use and we use this on
the Wikipedia project um and I learned
it I learned it from those people mostly
but also in other projects is literally
just to take a random set of other
queries positive labels and just treat
them as negative for this label and this
actually works really well because
almost all the time a random document
from the IND index is irrelevant for a
query um and we can sample we can just
have our training set we don't have to
go and do extra extraction from the
search engine to pull these features
down we can literally just say oh well I
also have this golden retrieval travel
anxiety query and it's irrelevant for
these keybridge queries I'm just going
to sample and we sample like 50 and we
slot them in and that helps our model
like learn these patterns of um of of
negative results when things are
obviously irrelevant so that a really
key learning when we were doing this um
yeah and now our model can sort of see
this pattern of no title match is
irrelevant so it's really important when
you're doing LTR to really look to see
like what your feature balance is and
all that stuff uh and then finally we
had to sort of we would start with our
core features kind of like the normal
stuff that our uh our normal base
retrieval ranking is doing with solar we
we use solar by the way I don't think I
said that um and we would we could then
ask the question of how do I know if a
good if a feature is good to add to the
model that's always a question and you
can think about this not just in terms
of LTR but in terms of like should I
Index this because for regular retrieval
will it actually add information that
isn't already in the
index and if you think about this you
often have what's already in the index
might be really strongly correlated like
stuff that matches the title is almost
always going to match the body so the
body bm25 doesn't always add much more
information on top of the title because
things that are in the title are often
always in the body right so that's
that's not necessarily for an ml model
lots of great new
information but what might be really
good information is when there's no
correlation so here we have the number
of votes and obviously you know the
number of votes may have nothing to do
with a title bm25 score for a given
query there's going to be good stuff
about that topic there's going to be bad
stuff about that topic um and so these
are not correlated at all and think
about what that means to a model uh if
you add this to a model it's a new
signal that has nothing to do with your
existing signals and uh suddenly you can
make a decision if ndcg goes up when
your model or your off your train test
train split your your quality goes up
you can pretty strongly attribute it to
that feature as being a cause of
that uh and we actually would do this
like the is a subset of our features
doing like correlation so we can see
each feature correlating with each other
this is just a correlation Matrix and
what's interesting is you can see on the
bottom left uh and you can see the
diagonal every obviously everything is
correlated with itself very
strongly on the bottom left we have
these zones of like the vote count the
comments count how old something is and
you can see how those things actually
kind of correlate uh
but they don't correlate with these
other features that are like you know
bm25 features so it's adding information
on top of those so we spent time
analyzing and which features and we add
them and then of course when we add
features to the model this is just a
simple pairwise classification um of
relevant irrelevant it's not even um
what we necessarily put into production
but we can see oh this improved it seems
like this model is reasonable and useful
to add or this feature is useful to add
to the to the index
um and finally I'll just mention the
model architecture I think model
architecture is sometimes sometimes
interesting but also it's getting all
these practices right is often more
important um but we use a we actually
have a deep learning model that just um
because it's important these things are
important to your model architecture
you're optimizing a listwise thing like
a ranking getting right that's a
fundamental difference between learning
to rank and non-learning to rank ml and
then you have to sort of handle the fact
that a lot of features will always you
just have to be resilient or correlated
features not all model architectures can
do that very well um and there's
nonlinear relationships between things
often it's like if this query seems to
be about a recent topic then this these
signals these ranking signals matter
more otherwise it may be that there's
just informational thing and I want to
know the best headphones and that's a
longer tail thing so relevance is not
one formula it's a very nonlinear if
then branching situation so that's why a
lot of gradient you know you see a lot
of tree based models um so we're using a
lambdamart loss which is you can go
learn about it there's a bunch of blog
articles you can search on softwar
du.com actually you can't search on
software.com but you can go to Google
and search for
software.com and look for lambdamart for
great Notebook on that um but we
actually are using a deep learning model
with that loss
function so with that quick tour I'm
going to turn things over and we're
going to talk about getting things into
do the yeting part into production
so awesome thanks Doug uh so how do we
get LTR at Reddit off the
ground uh so add Reddit we use solar uh
so naturally uh we wanted to consider
solar's native LTR plugin uh which can
handle both feature calculation and
model inference uh to rerank the top end
results um however we also had the opt
of reranking outside of solar with
reddit's existing ml
infrastructure uh we had a lot of
criteria to consider uh when deciding if
we wanted to use the LTR plugin uh
ultimately we focused on query dependent
features and time Horizon of content uh
as the main reasons for picking uh solar
LTR uh it was important for us to get
something out the door quickly uh and
having feature calculation and model
inference together natively in a plugin
uh was really
appealing uh so what does this look like
under the Hood uh the configuration
consists of Json uh that specifies where
our feature store lives uh and most
importantly what this feature looks like
uh in solar query syntax uh for our
first pass we pick straightforward
features like title bm25 uh comments
count self text match that kind of
stuff uh for model training we sent
samples of our query stream against a
solar LTR cluster for feature logging uh
and once the model was trained uh we
deployed it as a config update and
rolled it out to the entire
cluster uh for inference we add an extra
rerank RQ parameter to our solar query
to invoke the LTR plugin uh this tells
solar to rerank the top end results
after the initial
retrieval um so now that we've run
through the details of what's Happening
under the hood uh let's take a step back
to see what the entire system and
testing looks
like uh this is a simplified view of
what our request flow looks like uh our
query traffic is passed through a
microservice which handles things like
normalization filters uh and now
reranking uh before forwarding the
request for our Solar
cluster uh before we begin uh any kind
of testing at scale uh we need to answer
one question uh should we rerank traffic
in the same cluster where we handle non-
reranked production traffic or should we
spin up a separate cluster and do the
reranking there in
isolation uh we asked ourselves what are
the most important sticking points for
that decision we could jump start the
project by using a single cluster which
we already had uh which would give us an
accurate read on latency and also allow
us to presumably vertically scale out of
any performance problems we see uh on
the other hand this would slow down
development by forcing us to coordinate
our changes with non-ltr work um which
would be a headache we would also risk
taking down the entire prod cluster if
we had issues with reranking if we used
a single
cluster uh so naturally we decided to
use a single
cluster uh hindsight is 2020 um but at
the time we thought latency and dollar
cost were the most important things to
get right um spoiler alert it turns out
safety and development isolation are
much more important uh but we'll get to
that
shortly uh so our first attempt at
productionizing LTR at Reddit uh
prioritize latency and dollar cost by
using a single cluster uh we really
wanted to make sure that the latency
readouts where testing would accurately
reflect uh what we would see with
production scale pressure and traffic
flowing through the cluster uh however
we also wanted to test LTR without
returning suboptimal results to users uh
we knew our first few attempts would be
far from perfect so we needed a way to
decouple these concerns uh and test
freely without worrying about damaging
our Topline metrics uh to facilitate
this we started using a technology
typically used for service level
proxying uh for shadow traffic through
the system and that looks something like
this uh so we've been using Envoy as our
application proxy layer at Reddit uh
which felt like the perfect tool to use
for mirroring traffic uh we set up a
mirror policy that would duplicate our
query traffic and forward this to a
separate set of Shadow kubernetes pods
uh these pods would talk to the same
solar cluster which would reform perform
the reranking the main benefit of this
approach is the responses from the
shadow pods will be thrown away so the
end user experience would not be
impacted while we continued our
testing uh however uh once we began
dialing up Shadow traffic uh we began
running to large latency increases uh
which led to down replicas down shards
uh and widespread casting
failures uh this kills the solar
so uh once we recovered we made the
decision to create a separate cluster
specifically for LTR uh to focus on
safety development isolation instead we
accepted there would be a Delta between
latencies across the DU clusters which
we would deal with later during analysis
uh this would also allow us to safely
tune things like the thread module and
GC settings without impacting non-ltr
workflows uh once our shadow traffic
testing looked good we moved to AB user
testing splitting a percentage of
incoming traffic for
ranking uh and now I'll hand it over to
Chris who will talk about uh some of the
problems with
scaling
thanks so yeah once we started actually
dialing up our Shadow traffic uh things
were not smooth no there'll be a slide
don't
worry empty space focus on
me um and yes we killed solar a few
times so we had to do some tuning which
I'll go
over uh so to give you a little more
context I'm actually curious I want to
pull the room how many people here are
running
solar oh a fair number of people in the
audience so you may have experienced
some of the same things uh that we have
um so read it off operates solar
clusters to just give you some
background on what we're running uh that
receive hundreds to thousands of queries
per second and we index new documents in
real time uh solar as many of you know
it's a Java based search engine that
needs its uh Java virtual machine
garbage collection tune quite well to be
able to perform at scale uh especially
when you're serving your real-time
traffic um and for those not familiar
garbage collection is the process of
reclaiming previously used memory to be
used again something application should
do frequently but not uh but quickly so
it doesn't impact other important work
like say handling queries and this is
foreshadowing to what one of our
problems was uh and to handle our scale
we uh we configured garbage collection
GC and solar to to run fairly smoothly
one of the first things we ran into was
the old generation would often grow too
large and start starving the jvm's
ability to create short-lived objects
which are what you need when you're
serving lots of lots of queries lots of
uh ephemeral
work unfortunately those changes didn't
fully fix our stability issues on our
clust
we were serving ranking traffic with the
LTR
plugin and to uh to understand why I'll
go a little bit more into background on
how LTR works it's uh first it's going
to issue the the actual query that we
want uh the want to get uh to for
retrieval get the top end documents that
were that were that are relevant per
Shard and then we are reranking all
these all these documents uh in a second
pass issuing even more queries to
compute some ml features which we're
then sending to Mr ml model and and then
we're going to return your reranked
documents and remember remember that our
challenge is to try to get this to run
on thousands of queries per second
dozens of features 19 years billions and
billions of posts and to do this without
solar falling
over uh and it did many many times and
I'll take you through one specific
example of how it
did so normally on our clusters that
were not running reranking uh on for
solar when we increase traffic this is
just a look at the the total number call
uh requests that are being handled by
one of our clusters when we increase
traffic slowly we'd see some stress
that's indicated by slightly increased
garbage collection pause times frequency
and some slightly higher query latencies
but usually the solar noes stay online
the follow nodes would keep in uh keep
up with the updates from their leaders
and the cluster would generally be
reliable with LTR not so much um every
time we started to ramp up traffic on
the cluster it would invariably enter a
death spiral where
in uh and here show we I'm showing
garbage collection uh the amount of time
spent doing garbage collection uh per
node the amount of pause time would
would increase rapidly to a point where
it was taking too long garbage
collecting so it's not doing enough
other work like say serving queries the
fer follower nodes would then get too
far behind their leaders and they would
need they realize oh we missed some
updates we need to start replicating
which would add even more work to that
core jvm which is trying to run this
during which uh GC times would again of
course increase uh because of that and
we we would repeat this cycle until
individual nodes and then whole shards
were down we're not able to serve
traffic and we'd have to press F to pay
respects and intervene manually to try
to get those nodes back online so we had
to do some thinking so try to figure out
what was actually going on we wanted to
look a little bit uh close uh closer at
a smaller increase in traffic let's not
just ramp all the way let's just look at
like F5 10% uh bump in traffic and see
look deeper at the
effects we noticed that we had a
disproportionate jump in the average
amount of time we're spending uh garbage
collecting just by doubling that traffic
from 5 to 10% we got three times as much
time spent garbage collecting not ideal
worse yet that increase in time was
spent uh in time spent and the frequency
wasn't stable it was slowly increasing
which would invariably cause that death
spiral that I mentioned earlier it
looked like we had issues with GC
throughput and we wanted to try to fix
this quickly during this project we
wanted to get it off the ground so we
tried throwing nodes at it we tried
vertically and horizontally scaling to
no avail but realizing that we need to
look at some other some other
performance optimization techniques
critically the most important one is we
asked uh what in what way can we do less
work report another way can we put less
load on garbage
collection we dove into uh what was
different about this cluster reranking
are the Clusters working pretty fine
what do our what extra work is this
doing we focused on the LTR features
themselves we know this cluster runs
well with ranking turned off are some of
our reranking features that we're
calculating during query time are they a
little too
expensive and we started compare this
cluster to some of our other clusters
and noticed that uh in
particular um one of our uh the filter
cache specifically seem to be
something that looked quite a bit
different um people say that the
internet is a Ser of tubes no it's
actually a bun of caches including this
one which is very important to try to
keep solar actually performing
well uh the filter cache just uh just
Stores um stores filters that have pre
previously been used so it doesn't have
to go back to disk or or back to it's in
more efficient memory structures but uh
for being able to use at at query time
and when we increased our reranking
traffic we saw that the amount of items
in the filter cache which is on the far
right that kind of green line that just
ballooned
astronomically um we also saw that there
was a fair Fairly high on the left hand
side a fairly High number of Misses cash
misses that were
occurring and uh and we're getting about
a 3X jump in the in the amount of items
that we're putting in that filler cache
for twice the traffic and uh all of this
is uh we began to suspect is maybe just
putting a lot of shortlived items in
that cash that that then need to be
garbage
collected taking a look at the actual
the actual uh hit rate for that cach it
was at about 75% on average uh for the
learning to rank plugin and we get
around 86% without the learning to rank
uh plugin which is 10% 10% different
which is fairly significant in terms of
performance
um then we wanted to so knowing now that
maybe this is this is something we
should suspect we wanted to take a look
at what is the LTR plugin actually doing
itself
internally so we dove into both the the
uh the features that we're using and
some of the code here's one of the one
of the features that that we use um when
to re ranking a query and remember that
uh so um we're going to
be uh so in this
case the uh the careers themselves are
fairly simple
um but there because there are four
specific documents in a document set
they're maybe not going to be fairly
reusable we saw in the code so it does
look like this is going to fill up our
cach with a bunch of items that are
going to be just filter our filter cach
with a bunch of items that are going to
be evicted later specifically we have
some features that uh not all of our
features do filter queries but this is
an example of one of them that
does and we and in our case we have 46
uh we issue 46 solar queries per query
uh six of them are filter queries like
this uh so we have the potential to add
a lot of a lot of different things into
uh into that cache and we were we
weren't quite sure is the um is this
plugin actually uh caching this
information we dug into the uh into the
code itself and found that Yes actually
there's a calls a method called get doc
set which the Javas the Java do
description reads if the answer is not
cash it may have been inserted into the
cache as a result of this call because
it's cash aware so we strongly suspected
that yes it was filter these these
features were perhaps a little bit more
expensive than we wanted they were
making uh filter query calls or queries
with Filter queries in them and probably
evicting them evicting a lot of those in
in the cach and causing a lot of
pressure on garbage collection and our
long GC pause times but it the issue
could have also just been the 46 other
queries that were issuing uh per query
or just any of the field of queries that
are used in the um uh as the actual
career itself any of those could have
been the actual issue so we we thought
let's try to design an experiment to
test which is what is truly the issue
here so we thought let's try a few
different variations of our how we're
doing reranking let's do exactly what we
were doing before so reranking with all
of our features uh we know this is going
to cause some high GC and we're going to
try just turning it off entirely issuing
the query itself self but no actual
reranking uh then we're going to try
reranking but uh we're going to Omit
what we think is the issue those filter
queries in our features H but we kind of
want those features uh spe to use those
so we're going to try a fourth variant
as well one where we we are reranking
but we're specifically telling solar to
not cache those
queries so trying this out uh we've got
another diagram of our garbage
collection with time on the on the
x-axis we observed that that there was a
a fairly large difference between these
starting off we kind of ramped up our
traffic from 5 to 10% uh and we observed
our high GC times again increasing to
the point where we would enter our death
spiral we saw just turning off reranking
our GC times plummeted to really nice
low levels awesome uh there was a short
uh bump in in GC time when we changed
our configuration to prepare for the
next two tests we then looked at um uh
trying out uh those those two other
variants let we tried using
um the uh turning on LTR again but using
uh none of the filtered query features
and we saw there was a jump in garbage
collection but not as high and not as
well shown here but crucially it was not
increasing it was a stable amount of
garbage collection so we thought hey
awesome maybe we confirmed that these
are going to be the issu
but we still want those features so we
tried the version that specifically says
run the filtered queries but just don't
cach those the results and the result
was quite uh quite similar in terms of
garbage
collection which was great news means we
can probably use we could probably use
those uh those features still just they
need to stay out of the filter
cache and how did that actually affect
the um the filter cache itself well here
we can see uh on the our far right side
the amount of items that we were putting
into it again when we were doing the the
normal just turning our regular LTR on
balloon exactly as we expected turning
it off started to empty empty the amount
of items in that cache also as expected
but we we thankfully nicely saw that um
we didn't build up massive amounts of
items in that cache when we were not
using the features at all no fq or when
we told it specifically to not cash
which is great also in the the version
which without caching our searcher warm
up time was thankfully SP stayed nice
and low and you can probably see there
was a massive drop in the number of uh
the number of Misses in the filter query
cach we also found that our hit rate
increased when we did this because uh
because it looks like not a lot of the
items in the filter cast that were being
inserted by LTR were particularly useful
they were dragging down the average hit
rate by quite a bit so we were now able
to get 9 a 95% hit rate exceeding even
our other cluster at the time and
throughout all this
we're even able to get pretty decent
latency the um those garbage collection
times uh how those often show up to
users is what you can see uh between the
on when we started ramp traffic and the
offs side occasionally you'll get longer
uh longer spikes in latency when we have
to stop the world in some
cases that that occurred when we were
doing when we were throwing things in
that filter cache later on except for
the part where we changed configs no
massive latency spikes
so with those results in hand we were
pretty confident that we could be able
to start adding more load to this
cluster and uh we solved just one of the
many reasons why our solar clusters were
were
failing so specifically for just just uh
for some info things some takeaways for
near realtime query indexing and solar
GC performance the both this through
Lany is incredibly important for
stability and when optimizing
performance try to look at what you can
avoid doing try to remove some work look
at your and the learning toing plugin in
in specific or in other machine learning
if you're doing things online look at
the cost your features as they're being
computed and the potential effects on
both intermediate like the filter cache
or transitive dependencies like the
jvmgc and see what could be how those
affect could be affecting things and
maybe you'll have more success than us
initially and I'll pass back to Doug to
now talk about next steps now that we're
yeting to the Moon um yeah so we started
to to really ramp up our AB testing uh
uh flow through this year as you can see
those dates there and I feel like every
LTR talk especially a real LTR talk has
like something like this where you kind
of like get to a baseline where it's
sort of maybe better but really it's
neutral and it's not significant it's
like the plateau like the plateau of
Despair so um we got to a point where
offline said some of these should be
better than our Baseline and and it
turned out not to be true we did a lot
of soul searching around this um and one
thing that really the main takeaway
another big LTR takeaway when you're
doing manual relevance work you can
you're sort of like even subconsciously
doing a lot of lgtm looks good to me um
even if you're 80% Guided by ndcg
improvements you're like well that's
still pretty good I think that's better
the team likes these results better I'm
going to put it into an EV test when
you're doing Mr ml is pretty stupid it's
just like taking in the training data
and like trying to make ranking better
right um you're giving it tons of
examples in bulk and those examples
better be
spoton um and the other thing the the
examples need to be weighed by frequency
whereas when I'm doing like my manual
tuning and be like well here's what it
looks like on head queries here's how it
looks like on tail queries it seems
neutral here better here let's ship it
and see what happens but when I'm doing
training it's it's like I really need to
get these very frequent queries right um
and these tail queries uh maybe a little
bit less important and so on so that
that change that will result in certain
AB test outcomes so we did a lot of soul
searching and the other thing that
really came up that you might think
about if you're like go on Google one
thing that social search has that I
think a lot of search doesn't the serps
really change a lot so often when we're
dealing with training data in other
contexts I can like aggregate 30 60 days
of clicks or whatever and reconstruct
what a typical Ser looks like by like
just saying like sorting by the
judgments and saying like what was most
relevant over the last 30 days that
doesn't really work in Social search
everything is changing all the time very
fast and we would have some queries that
would have um like a thousand different
results enter unique posts coming in for
like a query like you know a prominent
politician or something just like
constantly changing because people are
always posting news about that
topic um and that's a bit different than
like even e-commerce search sometimes
you you might your SE might change a
little bit but it's not going to change
so much and you think about this like
this is the
typical way that people train get this
stuff they'll have a click model or
something which is just taking these
specific individual search and actions
and sort of like averaging them or
aggregating them over some days and then
turning that into a label that's then
trained on and uh this works actually in
like I would say a lot of search
applications where we're running into
problems is like just how much these
change and just aggregation is hard to
do you over a meaningful amount of time
so you really we're getting away from
that this is like all future work and
what we're really want to do is get away
from using the some synthesized labels
so just like taking the serps directly
the search result Pages directly and
getting the features for that exact
occurrence appending those to the right
of this thing for each search result and
treating that as a single training
example so as someone searches and we
know what the vote count of the thing
the votes were or the how many comments
something got what the title bm25 of
that time we're going to put that all in
our in our data warehouse make that a
training example and just train directly
on that instead of trying to do any
click modeling um it's a lot more data
and we need to think about doing feature
extraction every time a search happens
so that's those are some downsides the
other nice thing about this is there's a
lot more context on these rows we have
the user ID we have uh the date
something happen on we know that a
search happening in this very specific
context with these very specific
features uh results and these things
being clicked or not clicked um so we're
moving maybe to this sort of notion of
our training
data um the other thing is
uh yeah so we have this notion um you
may have heard especially uh if you've
read AI power search or have familiarity
with like anything from Lucid works or
anything there's a notion of signals and
signals sometimes is an overloaded term
but in this case signals refers to
things that we know historically have
tended to perform well for a given uh
query one thing that we learned our
initial plan was LTR is going to be
applied to the longtail of search
results that don't have signals if it
has signals we feel like we're just
going to ignore that at least for now
and like let the signals take over um
and we learned that signals actually
cover something like upwards of 75% plus
of the search interactions which was a
big surprise to us and um so we sort of
have to figure out a plan for
incorporating this data of like what has
gotten recently is usually relatively
recently getting back to that Dynamic
Ser notion what has been engaged with
recently for these uh
posts and you could about think about
signals is like it's actually like an
overfit just a bunch of labels of like
what it memorizing what was good at one
point we of course want the model to
sort of generalize so it's a bit of a
tricky thing to get right because if we
just give it signals it's sort of like
letting the model cheat so we have to
sort of balance out when we hold out
signals and when we give the model
signals when we're training so that it
can like learn General patterns that
aren't just like memorize stuff on the
left of What's um with
signals um yeah like I said that covers
way more so yeah we're going to be next
up this is actually hopefully the next
round of ab tests uh is to train with uh
signals in addition to our core
retrieval and get the ideal mix of
signals and lexical as our next model
and that's it so uh
yeah thank you I want to mention by the
way quick plug uh I forgot to put a
slide for this the book that uh Trey
I've been helping with with Trey AI
powered search is going to be coming out
soon and I put a discount code for that
um if you so if you want to learn about
learning to rank there's a lot of great
content there but also signal boosting
and lots of other stuff so check out AI
powered search
[Applause]
so all right and we have a 30 seconds
for
questions but 15 minutes until the next
talk so there is an opportunity for
numerous questions as long as I don't
start L
stavos on your very first slide i m Zoom
people have to hear right on the first
slide or one of the first slides you
have the model where you do the LTR on
the lexical features and you have the
vector on the right why is the vector
score not an input to the LT why is it
not a feature in the
LTR yeah I I that's something we hope to
do in the in the future definitely it's
uh just we have like what we the other
thing that we did mention we've got we
could potentially be doing inference at
different levels too for a model so
there's sort of we we could have a base
ranker and then later farther down we
might have a ranker that sort of figures
out how to combine these things um but
it's totally you're totally right that
totally could be a thing there's no
reason not to
thanks hi um this is maybe just a more
of a clarification when you talking
about the training data I might have
just missed because of lack of
familiarity but you talked about giving
what I understood to be like counter
examples of irrelevant queries
um would you mind just kind of recapping
that again a bit was it basically like
for a given query you give examples of
um like a query that doesn't
work yeah
yeah it's within a query actually
results that are irrelevant so sometimes
you have just um so we have results that
are irrelevant but they also match the
title sometimes that happens right so if
you look at that if you're a model and
you have to make a decision how do I use
title match without
that uh you won't use title match to
decide whether result is relevant
because there's nothing there there's no
decision to be made right you can't say
if it if you just see this data if you
see a tabless data a model can't learn
that title match for this keybridge
query matters but if we inject some some
various noise in there and some
different things from other queries it
can really learn that pattern and that
was something that really improved our
model performance early
on yeah per
feature exactly yeah and we don't we're
not smart enough to like make sure it's
balanced and everything we it's more
like we random we just randomly pick
some 50 things from other queries and
stick them in there and it it helps but
yeah we could probably be more
intelligent looking at the balance of
features and making sure we have
representation over all the
labels coming from Habib
Shu I'm curious how long it took them to
get the tuning issues right and what
they use for observability that helped
in figuring this
out um we are still working on some
issues so it's still ongoing but we've
uh We've Come fairly far it's probably
that we unfortunately tried to do a
migration from solar 7 to solar 9 and
also from running on just ec2 to
kubernetes at the same time as also
trying to tune LTR dealing with a lot of
stuff um so it's still ongoing um but
the uh we use grafana internally to try
to to do a lot of um a lot of
visualization and we've got a lot of
people writing a lot of good queries and
visualizations to try to figure out uh
to diagnose
things do you guys ever see um like
having like a model fine- tune
automatically or do you think it always
has to have like a he in the loop as
part of the process of like fine tuning
the ATL
models yeah that's a good question
eventually I feel like it's good to
start with the human in the loop and
like gradually relax right now we very
much have a human in the loop um but
especially as we get to retraining um
the a whole topic of model monitoring
and like making sure your model's not
doing weird things where it becomes more
about like uh almost like monitoring a
production system to make sure it's not
going off the rails we're not at that
point yet but if we train models like
weekly or something we'd want to like
not so much like have a human approve
everything but more like have um
monitoring in place and observability to
know when things are like not good and
we should roll back to last week's model
or something
and question from Aruna
gooru a generic question on the LTR
plugin how does number of feature sets
affect latency and performance and how
can we improve
combine um so you can play with the
number of threads uh that the LTR model
is able to use and you can give as many
cores as you like to uh to the jvm in
that case so playing with those settings
can let you can help improve latency
with uh with various models in terms of
though the in terms of the number of
features though and how that affects
things I you may have a more insight
yeah just really quickly like one thing
that cliff and I spent a lot of time
doing early on was we look we would test
turning features on and off and trying
different scenarios to one latency and
we did find some expected unexpectedly
expensive features and took those out um
but it's only going to be like it's
literally the same as if you ran the
query directly to solar um and so I
often tell people say why is my LTR slow
and the most important thing is I think
it's good to take actually take the
features out of the LTR plugin and just
run them um as queries directly to to
solar and see what's expensive we found
that like things like rerank depth or
the model wasn't
necessarily that huge of course if you
get like reranked depth of a thousand it
can really impact things but what really
impacted things was like weird features
or like you know this filter query thing
or
whatever and final question from Mike
Henderson where can I find the discount
code say that again please the search
relevant slack opensource
connections.com
slack and and there is a discount code
in there so check out AIW search what's
that confence oh it's in hyack
conference yeah that's what I get for
typing it in the middle of my colleagues
giving a
talk thank you all very much let's thank
our speakers again
first